A Guide to the William C. Wooldridge papers, 1943-2022
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
William C. Wooldridge papers, 1943-2022
The Library of Virginia
53662
6.65 cubic feet (19 boxes)
William C. Wooldridge
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William C. Wooldridge, Norfolk.
Biographical Information
William C. Wooldridge was born 24 February 1943 in Miami, Florida, to Clarence Edward Wooldridge (1912-2002) and Easter Souders Wooldridge (1912-1977). Clarence Wooldridge served in the miltary and the family lived in Pennsylvania, Ohio, and Kansas, before finally settling in Lynchburg, Virginia, where William Wooldridge graduated from E. C. Glass High School n 1961. He graduated from Harvard University in 1965 and did a year of post-graduate work at the University of St. Andrew's in Scotland. Wooldridge graduated from the University of Virginia law school in 1969, then entered the military, serving as a lawyer from 1969 to 1973. Wooldridge joined Norfolk and Western Railway Company as a lawyer in 1973, working at the company's Roanoke, Virginia, headquarters. When Norfolk and Western and Southern Railways merged to become Norfolk Southern, Wooldridge relocated to the new headquarters located in Norfolk, Virginia. He became vice president, law, in 1996 and retired in 2000. Wooldridge married Joyce Norton 15 June 1968 and they had two sons.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1943-2022, of William C. Wooldridge of Norfolk, Virginia, containing articles, birth announcements, birthday cards, brochures, Christmas cards, clippings, letters, memorandum, post cards, programs, report cards, reports, statements, and other documents concerning Wooldridge's family, friends, education, legal career, historical and genealogical research, map collecting, travel, and social activities. Collection is divided into two series: Series I: William C. Wooldridge business papers, 1973-2000; Series II: William C. Wooldridge correspondence, 1943-2022; Series III: Writings, 1960-2022.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: William C. Wooldridge business papers, 1973-2000
Series II: William C. Wooldridge correspondence, 1943-2022
Series III: Writings, 1960-2022
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
William C. Wooldridge genealogical research papers, 1960-2015. Accession 51624. Personal papers collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
Contents List
- List of files: Wooldridge business papers, 1973-2000 and Wooldridge correspondence, 1943-2022, 1943-2022. (Folder 1)
- Series I: William C. Wooldridge business papers, 1973-2000., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  William C. Wooldridge business papers, 1973-2000, contain correspondence, memorandums, reports, statements, and other papers, concerning Wooldridge's career as an attorney for Norfolk and Western and Norfolk Southern railroads.
  Chronological
  - Business papers, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Business papers: equipment trust papers 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Business papers, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Business papers, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Business papers, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Business papers, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Business papers, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Business papers, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Business papers, 1991-1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Business papers, 1997-2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series II: William C. Wooldridge correspondence, 1943-2022., Extent: 17 boxes. (Box 2-18)
  William C. Wooldridge correspondence, 1943-2022, contain articles, birth announcements, birthday cards, brochures, Christmas card, clippings, letters, post cards, programs, report cards, and other documents. Papers detail Wooldridge's family life, his education, his career as a military lawyer, his career as a lawyer for Norfolk and Western and Norfolk Southern railroads, his interest in historical and genealogical research, his map collecting, and his and his family's travels.
  - Correspondence, 1943-1954 (Florida; Willow Grove, Pennsylvania; Canton, Ohio; Olanthe, Kansas) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1961 (Lynchburg, Virginia) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1961 (grade report cards) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1967 (academics) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, August-December 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, January-July 1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Military, 1965-1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Railroads in World War I, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, July-December, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Norfolk and Western correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January-July 1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, August-December 1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence--letters to Joyce Norton Wooldridge's parents, 1970-1972, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, January-May 1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, June-December 1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1972 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1972 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-April 1973 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May-December 1973 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, January-April 1974 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, May-December 1974 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence regarding house (Botetourt County, Va.), 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, March-October 1975 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, November-December 1975 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence--Brunswick Forge Road, Inc. (Botetourt County, Va.), 1982 (1980-1985) (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, January-May 1983 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, June-December 1983 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-March 1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, April-December 1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence--the Ehbauers regarding their daughters, exchange students who stayed with the Wooldridges, 1985-1987 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1986 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1986 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1987 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1987 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, January-July 1988 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, August-December 1988 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1989 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1989 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1990 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1990 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, January-May 1991 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, June-December 1991 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, January-August 1992 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, September-December 1992 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-April 1993 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May-December 1993 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, January-August 1994 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, September-December 1994 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Fort Norfolk Courier, Norfolk Historical Society, 1994-1995 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, January-March 1995 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, April-June 1995 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1995 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence--promotion to vice president, Norfolk Southern's law department, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-April 1996 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May-July 1996 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, August-December 1996 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January-March 1997 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, April-June 1997 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1997 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, January-July 1998 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, August-December 1998 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-May 1999 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, June-October 1999 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, November-December 1999 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January-July 2000 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, August-December 2000 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, January-June 2001 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, July-December 2001 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-April 2002 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May-September 2002 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, October-December 2002 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January-April 2003 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, May-September 2003 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, October-December 2003 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-July 2004 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, August-December 2004 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, January-March 2005 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, April-September 2005 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, October-December 2005 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, January-June 2006 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, July-December 2006 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-May 2007 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, June-December 2007 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, January-June 2008 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July-December 2008 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2009 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, January-June 2010 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, July-December 2010 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-June 2011 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, July-December 2011 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, January-September 2012 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, October-December 2012 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, January-May 2013 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, June-October 2013 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, November-December 2013 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, January-June 2014 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, July-December 2014 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, January-May 2015 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, June-December 2015 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January-April 2016 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, May-December 2016 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 2017 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 2018 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2019 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2020 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2021 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2022 (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Series III: Writings, 1960-2022., Extent: 1 box. (Box 19)
  Writings, 1960-2022, contain articles, book reviews, and poems written by William C. Wooldridge on economics, genealogy, history, maps, politics, and other topics. Also contains reviews of books written by Wooldridge. Also includes a volume of poems written by Easter Souders Wooldridge (1912-1977), arranged by William C. Wooldridge in 2022.
  - Oxford Furnace, The Critic (vol. LIX, no. 3), E. C. Glass High School, Lynchburg, Virginia, Spring 1960 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Liberal Reform and Horace Mann (vol. 2, no. 3, February 1964) and Progressivism During the World War (vol. 3, no. 4, May 1965), Harvard Conservative, 1964-1965 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Reconstructing Reconstruction, review of Kenneth Stampp, The Era of Reconstruction, Lynchburg News, 20 September 1965 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - The Critical Years and the Constitution, review of Forrest McDonald, E Pluribus Unum, Intercollegiate Review, May-June 1966 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - The Sound and Fury of 1896: Virginia Democrats Face Free Silver, Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, January 1967 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - The Penny Posts, Rally (vol. 1, no. 12), May 1967 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - The Last Soldier of the Civil War, unpublished, July 1967 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Annual Survey of Virginia Law: Evidence, Virginia Law Review (vol. 53, no. 7), November 1967 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - The Civil Aeronautics Board as Promoter, Virginia Law Review (vol. 54, no. 4), 1968 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Review of Staughton Lynd: Intellectual Origins of American Radicalism, Reading Guide, UVA Law School (vol. XXIII, no. 4), December 1968 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Legal Education in Virginia Before the Civil War, Legal Education Seminar, 14 January 1969 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Review of Stanley I. Kutler: Judicial Power and Reconstruction Politics, Virginia Law Review (vol. 55, no. 3), April 1969 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Origins of the Virginia Dynasty, review of Clifford Dowdy, The Virginia Dynasties, National Review, 15 July 1969 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - The Army Example, Private Practice, July 1974 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Uncertified Mail, review of Dorothy Ganfield Fowler, Congress and the Post Office, Inquiry, 20 March 1978 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Focus: Robert D. Stoner, The Torch (vol. 2, no. 2), Fincastle Presbyterian Church, Botetourt County, Virginia, April 1978 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - The Arbitral Function of Railroad Regulation, American Bar Association Journal (vol. 66), October 1980 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - The Single Product Rule and Rail Freight Transportation, Transportation Practitioners Journal, Summer 1985 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - A Ghent Cycle, Irene Leache Memorial, 68th Literary Contest, prize winners, and other light verse1986 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Blacksmiths First Develop Virginia's Coal, Norfolk Southern Focus (vol. 3, no. 2), 1987 (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - First Presbyterian Church, Norfolk, Virginia, unpublished, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - Balance Rail Competition--Norfolk Southern's commitment to NS Conrail, draft, 27-29 October 1996 (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - The Case of the Missing Presbyterians, Norfolk Historical Society Courier (vol. 8, no. 1), Winter-Spring 2001 (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - Review of Susan Dackerman: Painted Prints, The Portolan, Spring 2003 (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Ortelius's Chesapeake, The Portolan, Winter 2004 (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - The Bucholtz-Ludwig Map of Virginia, The Portolan, Spring 2007 (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - A Person of Worth and Integrity: John Worlidge, West Jersey Surveyor, The Portolan, Winter 2009 (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - Midlothian, The Virginia Genealogical Newsletter (vol. XXXVIII, no. 5), October 2012 (Box 19, Folder 28)
  - Trouble in Mapland (with Marianne McKee), The Portolan, Winter 2013 (Box 19, Folder 29)
  - Review of Joel Kovarsky: The True Geography of Our Country, Virginia Magazine of History and Biography (vol. 122, no. 4) 2014 (Box 19, Folder 30)
  - Letters to the Editor, Wall Street Journal, 20 July 2015 (Box 19, Folder 31)
  - Re-Stating John Henry's 1770 Map of Virginia (with Jay Lester), The Portolan, Spring 2016 (Box 19, Folder 32)
  - Possible British Origin of John Wooldridge, 2017 (Box 19, Folder 33)
  - Review of Christian J. Koot: A Biography of a Map in Motion, The Portolan, Fall 2018 (Box 19, Folder 34)
  - Review of Michael van Groesen and Larry E. Tice: Theodore de Bry--American, North Carolina Historical Review (vol. XLVII, no. 1), January 2020 (Box 19, Folder 35)
  - Letters to the Editor, Virginian-Pilot, 6 March 2021 (Box 19, Folder 36)
  - Review of Uncle Sam the Monopoly Man by William E. Cage, Intercollegiate Review, Summer 1971 (Box 19, Folder 37)
  - Review of The Wooldridge Family by Donald W. Moore, National Genealogical Society Quarterly (vol. 91, no. 3), September 2003 (Box 19, Folder 38)
  - Reviews of Mapping Virginia in Virginia Magazine of History and Biography (vol. 121, no. 2), North Carolina Historical Review (vol. XC, no. 3), and The Portolan (Spring 2013), 2013 (Box 19, Folder 39)
  - List of articles and books by William C. Wooldridge (Box 19, Folder 40)
  - Poems of Easter Wooldridge arranged by William C. Wooldridge, 2022 (Box 19)